Inventory of the R. Freeman Butts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- "Society's Expectations for School Instruction about the Constitution: An Historical Overview", 1980 (Box-folder 332: 7)
- "Time for a Revival of Civic Learning in the Schools", 1980 (Box-folder 332: 8)
- "International Human Rights: Vital Linkage between Global, Multicultural, and Civic Education", 1980 (Box-folder 332: 9)
- "Teacher Education in Africa: Modernization and Traditionalism Reconsidered", 1982 (Box-folder 332: 10)
- "The Revival of Civic Learning Requires a Prescribed Curriculum", 1982 (Box-folder 332: 11)
- "First Amendment Framers Didn't Mean for Us to Pray in School", 1982 (Box-folder 332: 12)
- "Teacher Education and the Revival of Civic Learning", 1982 (Box-folder 332: 13)
- "The Danger of Beguiling Half-Truths: The First Amendment Framers on Prayer", 1983 (Box-folder 332: 14)
- "Civic Learning in Teacher Education", 1983 (Box-folder 332: 15)
- Review of book by Amitai Etzioni, 1984 (Box-folder 333: 1)
- "Something Is Missing: The Civic Mission of American Education", 1984 (Box-folder 333: 2)
- Review of book by Morris Janowitz, 1986 (Box-folder 333: 3)
- Reply to article by Joe Nathan, 1985 (Box-folder 333: 4)
- Response to open letter by David Matthews, 1985 (Box-folder 333: 5)
- "Religion, Education, and the First Amendment: The Appeal to History", 1986 (Box-folder 333: 6)
- Letter to the editor, 1983 (Box-folder 333: 7)
- Correspondence with Robert Marquand, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 333: 8)
- "A History and Civics Lesson for All of Us", 1987 (Box-folder 333: 9)
- "The Moral Imperative for American Schools", 1987 (Box-folder 333: 10)
- "History and Civic Education", 1986 (Box-folder 334: 1)
- "Citizenship Must Be First among 'Jeffersonian' Goals", 1989 (Box-folder 334: 2)
- "A Rejoinder to Tozer's Draft Position Paper", 1993 (Box-folder 334: 3)
- "Kenneth Benne: The Compleat Teacher, or the Philosopher's Practice of Civic Virtue", 1992 (Box-folder 334: 4)
- "The Time Is Now: To Frame the Civic Foundations of Teacher Education", 1993 (Box-folder 334: 5)
- Kappa Delta Pi correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 334: 6)
- "The Politics of National Educational Standards", 1998-1999 (Box-folder 334: 7)
- Abstract of thesis, "The Development of the Principle of Election of Studies in American Colleges and Universities", 1935 (Box-folder 335: 1)
- "What Image of Man Should Public Education Foster?", 1957 (Box-folder 335: 3)
- "What Image of Man Should Education Foster?", 1959 (Box-folder 335: 4)
- "The Education of Teachers-If I Had My Way", 1959 (Box-folder 335: 5)
- "Education for a Free Society", 1960 (Box-folder 335: 6)
- "Philosophy and Objectives of Higher Education", 1960 (Box-folder 335: 7)
- "Latin American Universities and Teacher Training", 1964 (Box-folder 335: 8)
- "European Models for American Higher Education", 1970 (Box-folder 335: 9)
- "Education for Citizenship: Educational Goals and Curriculum Patterns", 1974 (Box-folder 335: 10)
- "Education for Citizenship", 1974 (Box-folder 335: 11)
- "Reflections on Forty Years in the Foundations Department at Teachers College", 1975 (Box-folder 335: 12)
- "Educational History in the Context of Reform in American Society", 1975 (Box-folder 335: 13)
- "Compulsory Education: History, Current Status, Trends", 1975 (Box-folder 335: 14)
- "Principles that Should Guide American Civic Education", 1975 (Box-folder 335: 15)
- "Twilight for Compulsory Education-And the Public School?", 1976 (Box-folder 335: 16)
- "The Idea of Public Education in the Revolutionary Era", 1975 (Box-folder 335: 17)
- "Liberal Education and the Need for a New Civism", 1976 (Box-folder 335: 18)
- "American Education in a Pluralistic Society", 1975 (Box-folder 336: 1)
- "Civitas: The Essence of HIgher Education In Urbem", 1976 (Box-folder 336: 2)
- "A Historical Perspective on Citizen Education", 1976 (Box-folder 336: 3)
- "The Case for American Public Schools", 1976 (Box-folder 336: 4)
- "The Future of Teacher Education in America: Historical Perspectives", 1978 (Box-folder 336: 5)
- "The Influence of Commissions on American Education", 1978 (Box-folder 336: 6)
- "Historical Perspective on Political Education in the United States, 1978 (Box-folder 336: 7)
- "The Progressive Malaise of Revisionist Historians", 1979 (Box-folder 336: 8)
- Reports to the Danforth Foundation, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 336: 9)
- "Liberal Education and the Revival of Civic Learning", 1980 (Box-folder 336: 10)
- "The Humanities and Citizenship in American Education", 1981 (Box-folder 336: 11)
- "A Rationale for Stressing Law-Related Values in the Education of Citizens", 1982 (Box-folder 336: 12)
- Unpublished opinion pieces, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 337: 1)
- "Paradoxes in Democratic Values", 1983 (Box-folder 337: 2)
- "Historical Perspective on the Civic Role of the School in American Society", 1985 (Box-folder 337: 3)
- "Historical Perspective on Education, Religion, and the First Amendment", 1985 (Box-folder 337: 4)
- "Lessons from History Regarding Citizenship Education and Character Development", 1985 (Box-folder 337: 6)
- "Education, Religion, and the First Amendment", 1985 (Box-folder 337: 6)
- "Analysis of Civic Education in the United States", 1991 (Box-folder 337: 7)
- "The Pledge of Allegiance: A Case for Studying the Constitution in Civic Education", 1989 (Box-folder 337: 8)
- Correspondence with Frank N. Freeman, 1945 (Box-folder 338: 1)
- Teachers College statements and history, 1940-1970 (Box-folder 338: 2-3)
- Lectures on religion and morality, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 338: 4)
- Lectures on meaning of a profession, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 338: 5)
- Lectures on segregation, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 338: 6)
- Lectures on education and freedom, 1960 (Box-folder 338: 8)
- Lectures on education and society, 1961 (Box-folder 338: 8)
- Teachers College searches for president, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 338: 9-11)
- Committee on Ethical Standards, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 338: 12)
- Correspondence with John H. Fischer and Robert Schaefer, 1966-1974 (Box-folder 338: 13)
- Notes on rights of minorities, 1975 (Box-folder 238: 14)
- Teachers College remembrances and correspondence, 1974-1999 (Box-folder 338: 15)
- Wingspread Conference on Global Education, 1976 (Box-folder 338: 16)
- Marginal notes on book by Walter Berns, 1976 (Box-folder 338: 17)
- Correspondence with Fred Newman, 1978 (Box-folder 339: 1)
- Conversation on educational vouchers, 1979 (Box-folder 339: 2)
- Commission for a National Agenda, 1980 (Box-folder 339: 3)
- Television appearance, 1979 (Box-folder 339: 4)
- Correspondence with Carnegie Foundation, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 339: 5)
- Turning Points in Education conference, 1981 (Box-folder 339: 6)
- "The Timeliness and Urgency of Goal III: Values", 1981 (Box-folder 339: 7)
- American Educational Studies Association conference, 1981 (Box-folder 339: 8)
- "Citizenship and Public Administration", 1983-1984 (Box-folder 339: 9)
- Jennings Randolph Forum, 1982 (Box-folder 339: 10)
- Wingspread Conference on Redefining General Education in the American High School, 1982 (Box-folder 339: 11)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1982-1999 (Box-folder 339: 12)
- "Public and Private Values in the Making of Citizens", 1983 (Box-folder 340: 1)
- Law in a Free Society summer institutes, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 340: 2)
- Notes on lecture by Mortimer Adler, 1983 (Box-folder 340: 3)
- American Educational Studies Association conference, 1983 (Box-folder 340: 4)
- "The Dilemma of Civic Learninmg in the Schools of a Pluralist Democracy", 1983 (Box-folder 340: 5)
- Background materials on history and civic education, 1984 (Box-folder 340: 6)
- Translation of Japanese article on R. Freeman Butts, 1984 (Box-folder 340: 7)
- Council for the Advancement of Citizenship meeting, 1984 (Box-folder 340: 8)
- "An Educational Reform Genuinely to be Thankful for", 1984 (Box-folder 340: 9)
- Correspondence with Louise Adler, 1985 (Box-folder 340: 10)
- "Liberal Reformation and Conservative Counter-Reformation", 1985 (Box-folder 340: 11)
- Americans for Religious Liberty correspondence, 1985-1995 (Box-folder 341: 1)
- Correspondence with Frank Newman, 1985 (Box-folder 341: 2)
- Project for Public and Community Service, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 3)
- American Educational Studies Association lecture notes, 1985 (Box-folder 341: 4)
- Correspondence with Brewster C. Denny, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 5)
- Bicentennial competition text, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 6)
- Federalist Society symposium, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 7)
- Conversation with Terrell Bell, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 8)
- Anne Lewis column, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 9)
- Articles by Robert Marquand, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 10)
- Correspondence with Geraldine Clifford, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 11)
- Correspondence with J. H. Doolittle, 1989 (Box-folder 341: 12)
- California task force on middle grades, 1986 (Box-folder 341: 13)
- "A History and Civics Lesson for All of Us", 1986 (Box-folder 341: 14)
- California History-Social Science Framework draft, 1987 (Box-folder 341: 15)
- Constitutional Roots, Rights, and Responsiblities conference, 1987 (Box-folder 341: 16)
- National Commission on Social Studies in the Schools meetings, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 341: 17)
- Statement at Robert Bork confirmation hearing, 1987 (Box-folder 342: 1)
- "The Original Intention of an Establishment of Religion'", 1987 (Box-folder 342: 2)
- California model curriculum for human rights and genocide, 1987 (Box-folder 342: 3)
- Lectures by Ernest L. Boyer, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 342: 4)
- Bradley Commission on History in Schools, 1988 (Box-folder 342: 5)
- "Democratic Values: What the Schools Should Teach", 1988 (Box-folder 342: 6)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 342: 7)
- History: A Story Well Told conference, 1988 (Box-folder 342: 8)
- Correspondence with Art Must, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 342: 9)
- Correspondence with Stephen S. Trott, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 342: 10)
- National Teacher Act, 1989 (Box-folder 342: 11)
- Correspondence, 1990-1996
  - Diane Ravich, 1990 (Box-folder 343: 1)
  - Bill Honig, 1991 (Box-folder 343: 2)
  - Lisa Ball, 1992 (Box-folder 343: 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996 (Box-folder 343: 4)
- National Assessment of Educational Progress, 1992 (Box-folder 342: 5)
- Correspondence with Thomas L. Dynneson, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 343: 6)
- Task Force on the Role of Civic Education, 1995 (Box-folder 343: 7)
- Conversation on National Public Radio, 1995 (Box-folder 343: 8)
- Center for Civic Education, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 343: 9)
- Comments on federalism, 1990 (Box-folder 343: 10)
- National Standards for Civics and Government, 1994 (Box-folder 343: 11)
- Framework for education for democracy, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 344: 1-4)
- Overview and outline of book by Larry N. Gerston, 2000 (Box-folder 344: 5)
- Correspondence with Chuck Quigley, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 344: 6)
- Outline of dissertation by Dense D. Gibson, 1999 (Box-folder 345: 1)
- Carnegie Task Force on Teaching as a Profession, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 345: 2)
- Documents on professional teaching standards, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 345: 3)
- National standards and teacher education, 1994 (Box-folder 345: 4)
- Teacher education and Center for Civic Education, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 345: 5)
- "Civic Learning for the Teaching Profession: Capstone for Educational Reform", 1984-1986 (Box-folder 345: 6)
- National Assessment of Educational Progress on Civics, 1999 (Box-folder 345: 7)
- Civics Framework for the 1998 National Assessment of Educational Progress (Box-folder 346: 1)
- National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education program standards for elementary teachers, 1998 (Box-folder 346: 2)
- California 12th grade civics and government course outline, 1992 (Box-folder 246: 3)
- California standards in history, 1998 (Box-folder 346: 4)
- Concept of liberty, 1999 (Box-folder 346: 6)
- Edison Project, 1994 (Box-folder 346: 7)
- Accelerated schools, 1994 (Box-folder 346: 8)
- Civic values, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 346: 9)
- Correspondence with Arthur Levine, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 346: 10)
- Teachers College reorganization, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 346: 11)
- Correspondence, 1983-1999
  - Ellen Lagemann and George Coutts, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 347: 1)
  - David G. Imig, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 347: 2)
  - Louis Benezet, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 347: 3)
  - Jared Stallones, 1999 (Box-folder 347: 4)
  - Donald Warren, 1985-1998 (Box-folder 347: 5)
  - David B. Tyack, 1983-1998 (Box-folder 347: 6)
  - Jack Jennings, 1998 (Box-folder 347: 8)
  - Steve Slossman, 1997 (Box-folder 347: 8)
  - Mary Rauner, 1997 (Box-folder 347: 9)
  - Mike Timpane, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 347: 10)
  - Ernie Boyer, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 347: 11)
- Oswego movement, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 347: 12)
- Iftikhar Ahmad, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 347: 13)
- Sound recordings, 1957-1993
  - Alexander Meiklejohn, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 348: 1-2)
  - R. Freeman Butts, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 348: 3-4)
  - Ernest L. Boyer, 1993 (Box-folder 348: 8)
- Video recordings, 1993-1998
  - R. Freeman Butts, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 348: 5-7)
  - Maxine Greene, 1997 (Box-folder 348: 8)
- "Twelve Tables of Civism", 1980 (Box-folder 349: 1-2)
- Notes and research materials, 1910-2001
  - Civic virtues and civil rights, 1975-1983 (Box-folder 349: 3)
  - Historical views of citizenship, 1967-1982 (Box-folder 349: 4)
  - Idea of the public, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 349: 5)
  - Idea of citizenship, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 349: 6)
  - Civism, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 349: 7-8)
  - Normative history, 1980-1994 (Box-folder 350: 1)
  - Conservative renaissance, 1985 (Box-folder 350: 1)
  - Normative history, 1980-1991 (Box-folder 350: 2)
  - Normative political science, 1971-1994 (Box-folder 350: 3)
  - Normative philosophy, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 350: 4)
  - Paideia, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 350: 5)
  - Synopticon, 1952 (Box-folder 350: 6)
  - Sidney Hook, 1984 (Box-folder 350: 7)
  - Normative sociology, 1976-1992 (Box-folder 350: 8)
  - Normative law, 1985-1993 (Box-folder 350: 9)
  - Religion and citizenshiop, 1986 (Box-folder 350: 10)
  - Political science in social studies, 1935-1989 (Box-folder 350: 10)
  - Citizenship and public administration, 1983 (Box-folder 350: 12)
  - Civicists, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 351: 1)
  - Common core of civic values, 1978-1986 (Box-folder 351: 2)
  - Public as an idea, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 351: 3)
  - Justice, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 351: 4)
  - Freedom and individual rights, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 351: 5)
  - Freedom, 1960-1995 (Box-folder 351: 5-6)
  - Hazlewood School District v. Kuhlmeier, 1988 (Box-folder 351: 7)
  - Oregon v. Society of Sisters, 1925 (Box-folder 351: 8)
  - Citizenship Education Project, 1952 (Box-folder 351: 10)
  - Mortimer Adler article on freedom, 1954 (Box-folder 351: 11)
  - Freedom bibliography, 1954 (Box-folder 351: 12)
  - Equality, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 351: 13)
  - School busing, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 352: 1)
  - Search for equality, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 352: 2)
  - Affirmative action, 1970-1996 (Box-folder 352: 3-4)
  - Equality, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 352: 5)
  - Desegregation, 1970-1989 (Box-folder 352: 6)
  - Diversity, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 352: 7)
  - Bilingual education, 1982-1995 (Box-folder 352: 7)
  - Diversity, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 353: 1-3)
  - American pluralism and identity, 1995 (Box-folder 353: 4)
  - Multiculturalism, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 353: 5-6)
  - Due process, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 354: 1)
  - Privatization, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 354: 4)
  - Authority and leadership, 1956-1989 (Box-folder 354: 5)
  - Participation and national service, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 354: 6)
  - Obligation and responsibility, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 354: 6)
  - William James, 1910-1977 (Box-folder 354: 7)
  - Participation, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 355: 1)
  - Truth, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 355: 2)
  - Patriotism, 1988-2001 (Box-folder 355: 3-5)
  - Special projections and organizations on standards and tests, 1988-1995 (Box-folder 355: 6)
  - Indiana Education Policy Center, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 355: 7)
  - Educational choice and vouchers, 1983-1999 (Box-folder 356: 1-3)
  - Curriculum, 1993 (Box-folder 356: 4)
  - Resurgence of choice, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 356: 5-6)
  - Coons voucher initiative, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 357: 1)
  - Morality, religion, and politics, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 357: 2)
  - Private vs. public schools, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 357: 3)
  - Miscellaneous articles on education, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 357: 4)
  - Local vs. state control of public schools, 1989 (Box-folder 357: 5)
  - History and principles of American political thought, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 357: 6)
  - Communitarian Network, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 358: 1)
  - Brevard Hand and secular humanism, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 358: 2-3)
  - People for the American Way, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 358: 4)
  - Leonard Levy correspondence and articles, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 358: 5)
  - Church and state, 1964 (Box-folder 358: 6)
  - First Amendment, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 358: 7)
  - Religious equality amendment, 1995 (Box-folder 358: 8)
  - Opting out, 1986 (Box-folder 358: 9)
  - Proposition 13, 1978 (Box-folder 358: 10)
  - Turning points, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 359: 1)
  - Religion and politics, 1978 (Box-folder 359: 2)
  - Williamsburg Charter Foundation, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 359: 3)
  - James Madison, 1947-1989 (Box-folder 359: 4-5)
  - Thomas Jefferson, 1950-1986 (Box-folder 359: 6)
  - George Washington, 1989 (Box-folder 359: 7)
  - Religious right, 1995 (Box-folder 360: 1)
  - Religion and conservative politics, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 360: 2)
  - Creationism and evolution, 1981-1994 (Box-folder 360: 3)
  - Politics and religion, 1983-1993 (Box-folder 360: 4)
  - Religious freedom, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 360: 5)
  - Religion and education, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 360: 6)
  - Religion, politics, and education, 1984 (Box-folder 360: 7)
  - Teaching religion in public schools, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 360: 8)
  - Televangelgate, 1987 (Box-folder 361: 1)
  - Debate on prayer in public schools, 1980-1995 (Box-folder 361: 2-7)
  - Equal Access Act, 1984 (Box-folder 361: 8)
  - Shared time, 1985 (Box-folder 361: 9)
  - Child care and religion, 1989 (Box-folder 361: 10)
  - New standards project, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 362: 1)
  - Bush's voucher plan, 1992 (Box-folder 362: 2)
  - National Teacher Act, 1989 (Box-folder 362: 3)
  - Civitas in liberal arts and teacher education, 1997 (Box-folder 362: 4)
  - Civic foundations of teacher education, 1993 (Box-folder 362: 5)
- New American Schools Development Corporation, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 362: 6)
- Ohio Department of Education, 1992 (Box-folder 362: 7)
- National Commission on Excellence, 1983 (Box-folder 362: 8)
- Center for the Study of the Teaching Profession, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 362: 9)
- Thomas B. Fordham Foundation, 1998 (Box-folder 362: 10)
- National Commission on Teaching and America's Future reprot, 1996 (Box-folder 363: 1)
- Study and articles by John I. Goodlad, 1979-1993 (Box-folder 363: 2-3)
- American Educational Studies Association, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 363: 4)
- Holmes Group, 1982-1992 (Box-folder 363: 5)
- Harris survey of public views on educational reform, 1986 (Box-folder 363: 6)
- Study and articles by Ted Sizer, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 363: 7)
- Ernest L. Boyer and Fred M. Hechinger, 1981 (Box-folder 363: 8)
- Research materials, 1975-1995
  - Cultures, Ideas, and Values (Stanford University), 1988-1995 (Box-folder 363: 9)
  - Allan Bloom, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 363: 10)
  - Political correctness, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 363: 11)
  - Teaching history, 1976 (Box-folder 364: 1)
  - Papers about George S. Counts, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 364: 2)
  - Reports about surveys of textbooks, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 364: 3)
  - Censorship, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 364: 4)
  - Studies of textbooks, 1975-1991 (Box-folder 364: 5)
  - Cultural literacy, 1987 (Box-folder 364: 6)
  - Civic learning, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 364: 7)
  - Curriculum design, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 364: 8)
- Writings by Gilbert T. Sewall, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 364: 9)
- Bradley Commission on History in Schools, 1988-1996 (Box-folder 365: 1)
- Social Studies syllabus for New York State, 1987 (Box-folder 365: 2)
- Writings by Frances Fitzgerald, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 365: 3)
- National Assessment of Educational Progress, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 365: 4)
- National Commission on Social Studies, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 365: 5-7)
- New York State framework on social studies, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 365: 8)
- Drafts of bicentennial text, 1986 (Box-folder 366: 1)
- Notes and research materials, 1978-1997
  - Republicans and conservatives on educational standards, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 366: 2)
  - President's summit on volunteerism, 1997 (Box-folder 366: 3)
  - Republican revolution, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 366: 4)
  - Clarence Thomas, 1991 (Box-folder 366: 5)
  - Notes on bicentennial conference, 1987 (Box-folder 366: 6)
  - David H. Souter, 1990 (Box-folder 366: 7)
  - Robert Bork, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 366: 8)
  - Rehnquist Court, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 367: 1)
  - Conservative counter-reformation, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 367: 2)
  - Emerging conservatism, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 367: 3)
  - New federalism, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 367: 4)
  - Reagan influence on federal courts, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 367: 5)
  - Liberalism and Democratic Party, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 368: 1)
  - New Right, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 368: 2)
- An International Framework for Education in Democracy, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 368: 3-8)
- Civitas International Civic Education Exchange Program, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 369: 1)
- Civitas seminar in Palermo, 1999 (Box-folder 369: 2)
- Civitas conference in Riga, 1997 (Box-folder 369: 3)
- Writings by Ghia Nodia and Larry Diamond, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 369: 4)
- Notes and research materials, 1976-2001
  - Citizenship and education in 28 countries, 2001 (Box-folder 369: 5)
  - 2000 election and Proposition 38 (Box-folder 369: 6)
  - Education in 2000 political campaign (Box-folder 369: 7)
  - Politics of national education standards, 1998 (Box-folder 369: 8)
  - Clinton transition, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 369: 9)
  - 1992 election (Box-folder 370: 1-2)
  - Ross Perot, 1992 (Box-folder 370: 3)
  - Family values and Dan Quayle, 1992 (Box-folder 370: 4)
  - Rodney King verdict and violence, 1992 (Box-folder 370: 5)
  - New federal policies on education, 1980 (Box-folder 370: 6)
  - Reagan administration on education, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 370: 7)
  - Conservative reform in education, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 370: 8)
  - William J. Bennett, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 370: 9-10)
  - William J. Bennett, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 371: 1-2)
  - Education as a political issue, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 371: 3)
  - Reagan Revolution, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 371: 4)
  - Politics and education, 1976 (Box-folder 371: 5)
  - National Assessment of Educational Progress test on civics, 1999 (Box-folder 371: 6)
  - Politics, national vouchers, and vouchers, 1998 (Box-folder 372: 1)
  - Urgency of public education, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 372: 2)
  - National standards and politics, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 372: 3-4)
  - Politics of educational reform, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 372: 5)
  - Politics of virtue, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 372: 6)
  - Politics of mistrust, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 373: 1)
  - Politics of virtue, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 373: 2)
  - Politics of free market in education, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 373: 3)
  - Free market in educational reform, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 373: 4)
  - Educational reform and standards, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 373: 5)
  - Republican Revolution, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 373: 6)
  - Role of federal government in public education, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 374: 1)
  - Clinton and education, 1992 (Box-folder 374: 2)
  - America 2000, 1991 (Box-folder 374: 3)
- Correspondence, 1983-1992
  - Educational Excellence Network, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 374: 4-5)
  - Chester Finn, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 374: 6)
- National Council on Education Standards and Testing, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 375: 1)